Guide to the Alexander Morgan Hamilton Family Photograph Collection [1895]-1948, n.d. (Bulk 1905-1948) PR 103
New-York Historical Society
Alexander Morgan Hamilton family photograph collection
[1895]-1948, undated (Bulk 1905-1948)
New-York Historical Society
Hamilton, Alexander Morgan, 1903-1970
PR 103
17 Linear feet (16 boxes)
Collection of photographic prints, albums, scrapbooks, and certificates documenting the social, private, and political activities of the family of Alexander Morgan Hamilton (1903-1970). Materials relating to Elizabeth Hamilton's former husbands, John Wanamaker, Jr. and C. Egerton Warburton, are also included.
Provenance
Gift of James Carr in 1979.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 20 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Alexander Morgan Hamilton, grandson of financier John Pierpont Morgan and great-great-grandson of the first Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, was active in New York City government, the New York Republican Party and a variety of civic and social clubs. Born in New York City in 1903, he graduated from St. Paul's School in 1921 and Harvard in 1924. He served as President of the New York Young Republicans Club and made an unsuccessful run for the state senate in 1930. Hamilton was appointed as Deputy Commissioner in Charge of Weights and Measures in New York City's Department of Markets in 1934; he was referred to as "one-dollar Hamilton" after requesting only a symbolic salary of one dollar per year for the position. A rift with Mayor LaGuardia prompted him to resign from the position in 1935. Hamilton served in the Marine Corps during World War II, eventually rising to the rank of major. In his later years he took an interest in conservation and preservation work, serving as president of the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society and as secretary-treasurer of the American Museum of Immigration at the Statue of Liberty National Monument. He received an award from the United States Department of the Interior for his efforts.
Alexander Hamilton received a divorce from his first wife, Katherine Comly Hamilton, in Reno in 1935, and later that same day married Elizabeth Peltz Warburton Wanamaker, the daughter of wealthy Philadelphian George Mifflin Dallas Peltz and widow of department store magnate John Wanamaker, Jr. In 1923, at the age of seventeen, Elizabeth Peltz was expected to make her debut in society, but instead eloped with C. Egerton Warburton, the son of Major Barclay Warburton, the mayor of Palm Beach, Florida. She was active in the Philadelphia social scene, taking part in charity events and drawing the attention of the press. Soon after divorcing Warburton in 1932, she married John Wanamaker, Jr. on the same day his divorce from his first wife was finalized.
Alexander Hamilton's family maintained a high profile in society and politics. Hamilton's older brother, Pierpont Hamilton, served in the Army Air Corps during World War I and won the Congressional Medal of Honor for his service as a Lieutenant Colonel in the Air Force serving in Africa during World War II. In 1946, Harvard University awarded him an honorary Master of Arts, citing his military accomplishments. Another older brother, Laurens Hamilton, was a New York state assemblyman. Hamilton also had two sisters. Helen Hamilton Woods married Police Chief Arthur Woods; Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton died tragically at the age of eleven in 1919 as a late victim of the Flu Pandemic of 1918. Hamilton's parents, William P. Hamilton (1869-1950) and Juliet Morgan Hamilton, daughter of John Pierpont Morgan, were wealthy New Yorkers who owned and operated Thirlstane Ranch in Salisbury Cove, Maine.
Scope and Content Note
The Alexander Hamilton Family collection spans the period from ca. 1895-1948 and primarily contains documents and photographs relating to the personal life and political career of Alexander M. Hamilton, the family and public life of his second wife, Elizabeth, and to a lesser degree the lives of Hamilton's siblings, Pierpont M. Hamilton, Helen M. Hamilton Woods, and Laurens Hamilton and his parents, William P. and Juliet Morgan Hamilton. Also included are some photographs, clippings and certificates relating to Elizabeth Hamilton's first two husbands, C. Egerton Warburton and John Wanamaker, Jr. The collection is divided into four series: Scrapbooks; Photograph Albums; Loose Photographs; and Certificates.
Arrangement
Scrapbooks and photograph albums are arranged chronologically. Photographic prints and certificates are arranged alphabetically by sitter or recipient.
Materials have been arranged into series based on format.
Missing Title
Series I: Scrapbooks
Series II: Photograph Albums
Series III: Loose Photographs
Series IV: Certificates
New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Upper class -- New York (State) -- New York.; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs.; Thirlstane Ranch (Me.); Photographic prints.; Telegrams.; Diplomas; Greeting cards; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Certificates.; Albums (books); Scrapbooks.; Upper class -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia.; Boats and boating; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Core, E. B., -1931; Davis & Sanford; Hamilton family; Hamilton, Alexander Morgan, 1903-1970; Hamilton, Elizabeth Peltz Warburton Wanamaker; Hamilton, Juliet Morgan, 1870-1952; Hamilton, Laurens; Hamilton, Pierpont M.; Hamilton, William Pierson, 1869-1950; Hasty Pudding Club; Kurtz, William, 1833-1904; Loy, Myrna, 1905-1993; MacDonald, Pirie, 1867-1942; Shearer, Norma, 1902-1983; Wanamaker family; Wanamaker, John, Jr.; Warburton family; Warburton, C. Egerton; Woods, Helen Morgan Hamilton
- Series I: Scrapbooks
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I dates from ca. 1923 to 1948; it is arranged chronologically. The scrapbooks of Elizabeth and Alexander Hamilton document their social lives and Alexander Hamilton's political career. The two scrapbooks from ca. 1923 and 1930-1934 predate Elizabeth Hamilton's marriage to Alexander Hamilton in 1935, and contain a variety of clippings which document Elizabeth's early elopement with C. Egerton Warburton and later marriage to John Wanamaker, Jr., as well as her participation in Philadelphia society and John Wanamaker's boating activities. Later scrapbooks from 1935-1936 and 1936-1948 contain clippings related to Alexander Hamilton's divorce from Katherine Comly Hamilton and immediate marriage to Elizabeth Hamilton.
  The Hamilton family's movements in society were often followed by the press, and newspaper clippings from the society pages are abundant in these scrapbooks. Also present are personal mementos, such as dried flowers from the couple's wedding, greeting cards, telegrams and personal photographs. Several of the scrapbooks, dating from 1934-1948 contain clippings which track the political careers of Alexander Hamilton and his brothers, Laurens and Pierpont Hamilton. One scrapbook dating from 1937-1947 concerns itself almost entirely with the Thirlstane Ranch in Maine, the Holsteins that William P. Hamilton raised there, and the elder Hamiltons' participation in the community. The clippings and other textual materials from the scrapbooks have been photocopied; the photocopies are located in Box 6. Researchers are encouraged to use these photocopies as surrogates due to the fragile nature of the originals.
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, telegrams and clippings relating to Elizabeth Peltz's marriage to C. Egerton Warburton and to Philadelphia society, [1923] (Box 1)
    General note
    See also: Box 6, folder 3
  - Scrapbook: Photographs and clippings on Elizabeth P. Warburton's marriage to John Wanamaker, Jr., boat racing and Philadelphia society, 1930-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    See also: Box 6, folder 4
  - Scrapbook: Clippings relating to Alexander Hamilton's political career, Laurens Hamilton and the Republican Party, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    See also: Box 6, folder 5
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, correspondence and clippings on the wedding of Elizabeth and Alexander Hamilton and Hamilton's political career, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
    See also: Box 6, folder 6
  - Scrapbook: Clippings on Elizabeth and Alexander Hamilton, Pierpont Hamilton, and New York society, 1936-1948 (Box 4)
    See also: Box 6, folder 7
  - Scrapbook: Clippings relating to Thirlstane Ranch in Salisbury Cove, Maine, owned by William P. Hamilton, 1937-1947 (Box 5)
    See also: Box 6, folder 8
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 1, [1923] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 2, folder 1, 1930-1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 2, folder 2, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 3, 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 4, 1936-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photocopies of clippings from Scrapbook in Box 5, 1937-1947 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series II: Photograph Albums
  Series II documents the social and personal lives of the Hamilton family; the photograph albums date from 1936-1948 and include some undated materials. The albums are arranged chronologically, with one undated album at the end of the series. Many of the albums focus on the couple's travels; one album based primarily on the couple's trips to Santa Barbara and Santa Monica, California in 1937, contains photographs of social events and parties, some of which include Hollywood celebrities Myrna Loy and Norma Shearer. Others include photographs of fishing and boating trips to Florida, Maine, and Europe as well as unidentified destinations.
  - Clam bake and fishing in unidentified locations, 1936 (Box 7)
  - California, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Hamilton family, 1937-1948 (Box 9)
  - Florida, fishing, [1938] (Box 10)
  - Fishing, boating in unidentified locations, [1939] (Box 11)
  - Europe, Maine and unidentified locations, undated (Box 12)
- Series III: Loose Photographs
  Series III consists mainly of portraits of the Hamilton family from 1895-1931; most are undated and unidentified. Loose photographs are arranged into subseries by size; thereunder, they are filed alphabetically by sitter, and by date, with unidentified individuals at the end. One folder of oversize portraits of Pierpont Hamilton is located in Box 15. Included are portraits of Pierpont Hamilton by Pirie MacDonald, portraits of Alexander Hamilton and his siblings as children by E.B. Core, and a variety of unidentified portraits of children and adults who are probably members of the Hamilton and Morgan families. Also included is one group portrait of Harvard College's Hasty Pudding Club of which Alexander Hamilton was a member.
  - Small Format
    - Hamilton, Alexander M.--Childhood portraits, by E.B. Core, [1905-1915] (Box 13, Folder 9)
      See also: Box 14, folders 28-29
    - Hamilton, Alexander M.--Childhood portraits, miscellaneous, [1905-1915] (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Hamilton, Alexander M.--Portraits, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Hamilton, Elizabeth Peltz Warburton Wanamaker, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Hamilton family--Portraits of children, by E.B. Core, [1895-1915] (Box 13, Folder 13)
      See also: Box 14, folder 30
    - Hamilton family--Portraits of children, [1895-1915] (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Hamilton, Pierpont M.--Childhood portraits, [1895] (Box 13, Folder 15)
      See also: Box 14, folders 32-33
    - Hamilton, Pierpont M.--Portraits, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
      See also: Box 14, folders 32-33 and Box 16, folder 41
    - Morgan, Harry, undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Nichols, Jamie, undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Olney, Sigourney B., undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Powel family, [1906]-1931 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Woods, Helen Hamilton, with children, undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
      See also: Box 14, folder 35
    - Unidentified children, undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
      See also: Box 15, folder 36
    - Unidentified children, undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified man with child, undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified men, 1910, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
      See also: Box 15, folder 37
    - Unidentified women, undated (Box 13, Folder 26)
      See also: Box 15, folder 39
    - Unidentified women with children, undated (Box 13, Folder 27)
      See also: Box 15, folder 40
  - Large Format
    - Hamilton, Alexander M.--Hasty Pudding Club of Harvard College, [1924] (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Hamilton, Alexander M. -- Portraits, undated (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Hamilton family--Portraits of children, by E.B. Core, [1895-1910] (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Hamilton, Laurens, undated (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Hamilton, Pierpont Morgan--Childhood portraits, [1910] (Box 14, Folder 32)
      See also: Box 16, folder 41
    - Hamilton, Pierpont Morgan--Portraits in uniform, some by Pirie MacDonald, 1917-1918, undated (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Olney family, 1919, undated (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Woods, Helen M. Hamilton, undated (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Unidentified children, undated (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Unidentified men, undated (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified wedding portraits, undated (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified women, 1923, undated (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified women with children, undated (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Oversize
    - Hamilton, Pierpont Morgan, some by Pirie MacDonald, undated (Box 16, Folder 41)
- Series IV: Certificates
  Series IV consists of four oversized certificates and diplomas (1909-1921) issued to Alexander Morgan Hamilton and John Wanamaker, Jr. by the DeLancey School in Philadelphia, St. Paul's School in Concord, New Hampshire, and the U.S. Army. The certificates are arranged alphabetically by recipient and thereunder by date.
  - Hamilton, Alexander M. -- St. Paul's School, New Hampshire, graduation, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 42)
  - Wanamaker, John, Jr.--Delancey School, Philadelphia, graduation, 1909 (Box 16, Folder 43)
  - Wanamaker, John, Jr.--Appointment to Captain in the Quartermaster Section of Officers' Reserve Corps of the U.S. Army, 1917 (Box 16, Folder 44)
  - Wanamaker, John, Jr.--Completion of Third Course at Army General Staff College, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 45)